Murray, William J.; Papers apap356
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
William J. Murray Papers
1927-1990
M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives
Murray, William J., 1908-1995
apap356
4.83 cubic ft.
This collection documents the professional work of William J. Murray, who served as assistant administrative director of the New York State Department of Civil Service from 1946-1952 and then administrative director of the Department from 1952 until his retirement in 1971.
Biographical History
Born in Brooklyn, William John Murray (1908-1995) was a graduate of the College of the Holy Cross and St. John's University Law School. In 1937, he married Kathleen Rogers and they had six children.
After initial jobs in journalism, Murray began working with the New York City Civil Service Commission as an examiner in 1934. He was promoted several times to positions with greater responsibility in New York City during the next 12 years.
Murray, followed by his family, relocated to Albany in 1946 when he became assistant administrative director of the New York State Civil Service Department. He served in this position from 1946-1952. Later he became administrative director of the New York State Civil Service Department from 1952 until his retirement in 1971. In retirement, Murray consulted on a number of assignments and projects.
Murray passed away in December 1995 at the age of 87.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains meeting minutes, correspondence, pocket calendars, legislative materials, speeches, reports, and subject files, the majority related to William J. Murray's service as assistant administrative director and then administrative director of the New York Department of Civil Service from 1946-1971. A significant portion of the collection is composed of Murray’s “Role ONE Over” (RONEO) or daybooks. These provide a robust history of the New York Department of Civil Service during Murray's tenure, with the exception of Class and Comps. There also are several files relating to consulting work Murray completed after his retirement from the Civil Service.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection is arranged alphabetically. There are no series.
Acquisition Information
J. Michael Murray donated the collection of his father's papers to the M.E. Grenander Department of Special Collections & Archives in 2015.
Access
This collection is unrestricted with the exception of one file listed on the finding aid.
Separated Materials
The archivist transferred several monographs, including Staff Report on the Department of Civil Service, State of New York, Temporary State Commission on State Activities and The Administration of the New York State Civil Service Law to the book division of Special Collections. They will be catalogued and included in the University Libraries' catalog.
Murray, William J., 1908-1995; Civil service -- New York (State); Correspondence.; Files by subject; Calendars
- Administrative Management Reports, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Agenda and Minutes of Division Head Meetings (1 of 2), 1956 October-1963 December (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Agenda and Minutes of Division Head Meetings (2 of 2), 1956 October-1963 December (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Alexander Falk, 1955-1956; 1975 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Biography, Undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Calendar, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Calendar, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1927-1929; Undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1930; Undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1932; 1934; 1936; 1938 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1940; 1944; 1947; 1964 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1967; 1971; 1979 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1980-1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1982-1984 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1985-1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Calendars, Pocket, 1988-1990 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Challenge and Change, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Civil Service 75th Anniversary Dinner, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- Civil Service Commission According to Merit and Fitness, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Civil Service Exams Taken, 1933-1944; 1953; Undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Civil Service Executive Division Addresses, 1966-1970 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- Civil Service General Records, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Committee Meeting Minutes, 1952; 1956-1960 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Connecticut, Director of Personnel Exam, 1957-1958; Undated (Box 1, Folder 24)
- Cornell- Executive Development, 1963-1964; Undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
- Course Notes, Production Management, 1942; Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
- Event Programs, 1959-1961 (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Exam Questions, Undated (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Foreign Doctors, 1961-1967 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Governor's Negotiating Committee, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Legislation Notes, 1949; 1951-1952; 1958; 1963 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Manpower, Steps to Relieve an Acute Shortage, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Michigan, Civil Service, 1959-1960; Undated (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Michigan, Civil Service Memorandum, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Michigan, Director of Personnel, 1957; 1959; Undated (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Michigan, Director of Personnel Notes, 1959-1960; Undated (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Michigan, Director of Personnel Records, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Miscellaneous Drafts and Memos, 1941-1976; Undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
- Municipal Personnel Society Review, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Municipal Personnel Society Review, 1962 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- New York City - Miscellaneous, 1939-1940; 1942-1945; 1950; Undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
- New York Civil Service Pamphlets, 1954-1958; 1972; Undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
- New York Public Personnel Council Annual Meeting, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- New York State Civil Service 75th Anniversary, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1945 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1950-1959 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1960-1963 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1964-1973 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1974-1977 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- New York State Civil Service Annual Report, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- New York State Civil Service Assembly, 1953 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- New York State Civil Service New Careers, 1968; 1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- New York State Civil Service Staff Report Reply, 1956 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- New York State Civil Service Reports, 1943-1968; Undated (Box 2, Folder 11)
- New York State Civil Service Review of the State Constitution, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- New York State Personnel Notes (1 of 2), 1946-1971 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- New York State Personnel Notes (2 of 2), 1946-1971 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- New York State Police Committee Grievances, 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- New York State Public Administration Internship Program Graduates, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Newspaper Advertisement Bills, 1959-1960; Undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Pennsylvania Civil Service Commission Oral Exam, 1969; Undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Personal Correspondence I (1 of 3), 1946-1959; Undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Personal Correspondence I (2 of 3), 1946-1959; Undated (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Personal Correspondence I (3 of 3), 1946-1959; Undated (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Personal Correspondence II (1 of 3), 1958-1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Personal Correspondence II (2 of 3), 1958-1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Personal Correspondence II (3 of 3), 1958-1971; Undated (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Personal Data and Mementos Before 1946, 1936-1945 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Personal Data and Mementos 1946 and On, 1946-1974; Undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Personnel Management Study, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- Personnel Management in the New York State Department of Taxation and Finance, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Public Administration and Administrative Management, 1964; Undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Public Personnel Association Blue Book, Undated (Box 3, Folder 4)
- Resumes, 1968-1970; Undated (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Retirement Papers, 1947; 1966-1971; Undated (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Retirement Party, 1970 October 13 (Reel 1)
- Reviewed Resumes, 1959 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- RONEO, 1946; Undated (Box 3, Folder 8)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1947; Undated (Box 3, Folder 9)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1947; Undated (Box 3, Folder 10)
- RONEO (1 of 3), 1948; Undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
- RONEO (2 of 3), 1948; Undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
- RONEO (3 of 3), 1948; Undated (Box 3, Folder 13)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1949; Undated (Box 3, Folder 14)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1949; Undated (Box 3, Folder 15)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1950; Undated (Box 3, Folder 16)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1950; Undated (Box 3, Folder 17)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1951; Undated (Box 3, Folder 18)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1951; Undated (Box 3, Folder 19)
- RONEO, 1952; Undated (Box 3, Folder 20)
- RONEO, 1953-1956; Undated (Box 3, Folder 21)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1957-1958; Undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1957-1958; Undated (Box 4, Folder 1)
- RONEO (1 of 3), 1959-1960; Undated (Box 4, Folder 2)
- RONEO (2 of 3), 1959-1960; Undated (Box 4, Folder 3)
- RONEO (3 of 3), 1959-1960; Undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
- RONEO (1 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- RONEO (2 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- RONEO (3 of 3), 1961-1962 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1963; Undated (Box 4, Folder 8)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1963; Undated (Box 4, Folder 9)
- RONEO, 1964; Undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1965; Undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1965; Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- RONEO (1 of 2), 1966; Undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
- RONEO (2 of 2), 1966; Undated (Box 4, Folder 14)
- RONEO (1 of 2 ), 1967; Undated (Box 4, Folder 15)
- RONEO (2 of 2 ), 1967; Undated (Box 4, Folder 16)
- RONEO (1 of 2 ), 1968; Undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
- RONEO (2 of 2 ), 1968; Undated (Box 4, Folder 18)
- RONEO, 1969; Undated (Box 4, Folder 19)
- RONEO, 1970; Undated (Box 4, Folder 20)
- RONEO, 1971; Undated (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Speech Material (1 of 2), 1944; 1948-1953; 1957-1968; Undated (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Speech Material (2 of 2), 1944; 1948-1954; 1957-1969; Undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Speech Notes, 1962; Undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Speeches, 1952; 1957-1968; Undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
- Strictly Personnel (1 of 3), 1952-1971 (Box 5, Folder 5)
- Strictly Personnel (2 of 3), 1952-1971 (Box 5, Folder 6)
- Strictly Personnel (3 of 3), 1952-1971 (Box 5, Folder 7)
- Talks, 1946-1953; Undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
- Talks, 1954 and On, 1954-1965 (Box 6, Folder 2)
- Time Sheets, 1944-1946 (Box 6, Folder 3)
- Travel Vouchers - RESTRICTED, 1947-1952; 1968-1970 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Must consult with an archivist before viewing this material.
- The Veterinary Service Notes (1 of 2), 1975-1946; Undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
- The Veterinary Service Notes (2 of 2), 1975-1946; Undated (Box 6, Folder 6)
- The Veterinary Service of the New York State Department of Agriculture and Markets, 1976 (Box 6, Folder 7)
- Visitors, 1946-1970; Undated (Box 6, Folder 8)
- Writings, 1942-1957; Undated (Box 6, Folder 9)
- Writings, 1958-1967; Undated (Box 7, Folder 1)
- Writings, 1967-1971; Undated (Box 7, Folder 2)